Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是斯科特-曼利
And once again I am wearing the dressing gown of doom
我又一次穿上了厄运的长袍
because some sort of rocket anomaly happened while I slept last night.
因为昨晚我睡觉的时候发生了某种火箭异常现象
So yes around 3 a.m that was a scheduled liftoff for Rocket Labs Electron.
所以 是的 凌晨3点左右是火箭实验室电子号的预定升空时间
It would be their 20th launch a launch nicknamed Running Out of Toes.
这将是他们的第20次发射 一次绰号为 "脚趾跑光 "的发射
Number 10 was Running Out of Fingers.
第10次是 "跑出手指"
It would be carrying a pair of black sky satellites or earth observation satellites
它将携带一对黑天卫星或地球观测卫星
and the biggest thing we were expecting from this was
而我们从中期待的最大的事情是
they were going to attempt to recover the booster stage in the ocean again
他们将试图再次在海洋中回收助推器阶段
and we're hoping to get possibly a live feed of the descent.
我们希望能得到下降过程的实况转播
Now that never happened.
现在这一切都没有发生
Now the rocket launch was initially delayed and went into a number of holds
现在 火箭发射最初被推迟 并进入了一些搁置阶段
because the weather wasn't great
因为天气不是很好
but then when it did lift off
但当它真的升空时
it seemed to execute successfully went through all the launch
它似乎成功地执行了所有的发射过程
performed through max q safely main engine cutoff and stage separation
安全地完成了最大Q值的主发动机关闭和级间分离
and then the second stage went out of control, right.
然后第二级就失去了控制 对
It spun out of control.
它失去了控制而旋转
So what what do we know.
那么我们知道什么呢
Well we actually have a couple of foot cameras on board
好吧 我们实际上有几个脚下的摄像机在船上
that gave us pretty much all the information we needed along with the telemetry.
给我们提供了几乎所有我们需要的信息 还有遥测数据
So there was an external camera on the outside of the second stage that looks down
所以在第二级的外面有一个外部摄像机 可以向下看
and that showed us most of the video of the launch.
并向我们展示了发射的大部分视频
Inside the interstage there was a camera that looks at the rocket nozzle
在中间级的内部有一个摄像头 看着火箭的喷口
and we've seen that for most of the flights.
我们已经看到了大部分的飞行
Now the one that looked at the nozzle froze during the stage separation
现在 观察喷嘴的摄像机在级间分离时冻结了
but the external camera showed a clean stage separation.
但外部摄像机显示了一个干净的阶段分离
A little bit of wobble which is normal
有一点晃动 这是正常的
and then as soon as the second stage Rutherford engine fired up
然后当第二级卢瑟福发动机启动时
the view just swivels around out of shot and the thing is spinning.
视线就在镜头外旋转 东西在旋转
And that's the end of it, right.
这就是它的结局 对
They can't recover from that.
他们无法从中恢复
If you look at the telemetry
如果你看一下遥测数据
you can actually see the velocity is sort of wobbling up and down every second or so
你实际上可以看到速度每秒钟都在上下晃动
so the thing got put into a spin from which it couldn't recover
所以这东西进入了一个无法恢复的旋转状态
and they probably just shut down the engine and let it fall into the ocean
他们可能只是关闭了引擎 让它掉进了海里
rather than let it continue firing its engine and potentially go out of its launch corridor.
而不是让它继续点燃它的引擎并有可能离开它的发射通道
Now as for what caused that spin
至于是什么导致了旋转
well if you look at the the camera that was inside the interstage that looked at the nozzle
好吧 如果你看一下在中间级里面的摄像头 它观察到了喷嘴
you can't really see very much.
你真的看不出什么
What you can see is that the engine does light
你能看到的是 发动机确实点燃了
but it doesn't seem to run very long and it cools down very quickly
但它似乎并没有运行很久 而且很快就冷却了
but if you actually compare it against the previous launch which was They Go Up So Fast
但如果你把它与之前的发射进行比较 也就是它们飞得那么快
and look at the exact position of that engine nozzle
并看一下那个发动机喷嘴的确切位置
you can see the nozzle is pushed over to the right in the one that launched last night.
你可以看到在昨晚发射的那枚中 喷嘴被推到了右边
Basically the second stage steers by gimbaling this nozzle, right.
基本上第二级是通过万向节来控制这个喷嘴的方向 对
So it can adjust the direction of the thrust
所以它可以调整推力的方向
and in this case it seems to have pushed it all the way over to the right
在这种情况下 它似乎把它全部推到了右边
and some sort of technical problem it could be that
还有一些技术问题 可能是
they couldn't stop the actuator from moving.
他们无法阻止推杆的移动
Maybe their sensor didn't detect that it moved all the way.
也许他们的传感器没有检测到它一直在移动
There's one suggestion sometimes that we've seen cases
有一个建议 有时我们已经看到了一些案例
where rockets have had the connections to adjust the position reversed
火箭的调整位置的连接被颠倒了
so that it was to steer to the right, steers to the left.
因此 它是向右转 向左转
That means it steers to the right more
这意味着它更多地向右转向
and eventually loses control very quickly.
并最终很快失去了控制
I don't think that happened in this case
我不认为这种情况发生在这个案例中
because if you look at the external camera
因为如果你看一下外部摄像机
the initial wobble carries it in one direction and then it compensates
最初的晃动将它带向一个方向 然后它进行补偿
and spins out of control in the other direction
然后在另一个方向上失去控制的旋转
so that's not what happened.
所以这不是发生了什么
I don't think.
我不这么认为
So yes that's unfortunate
所以是的 这是不幸的
because Rocket Lab's Electron has been a very successful small sat launcher
因为火箭实验室的电子号已经是一个非常成功的小型卫星发射器了
and it's really now getting to position where it's going to be having some serious competition out there
而且它现在真的到了一个位置 它将会有一些严重的竞争
and they can ill afford to have a failure like this on their chart.
他们不能承受在他们的图表上出现这样的失败
Now on the bright side Rocket Lab have confirmed that they've got the booster.
现在好的一面是 火箭实验室已经确认他们已经得到了助推器
The booster landed safely in the ocean.
推进器安全地降落在海里
And they're working on recovery operations right now.
他们现在正在进行回收工作
I'm not sure what we'll get to see from it
我不确定我们能从它身上看到什么
but one thing I do hope to see is the view from the interstage after stage separation
但我确实希望看到的是级间分离后的景观
because we got this for the previous recovery.
因为我们在之前的回收中得到了这个
And this was a marvelous piece of video.
而这是一段了不起的视频
It looks beautiful watching the rocket separate off cleanly and then light its engine
看着火箭干净利落地分离 然后点燃它的引擎 这看起来很美
and you can hear that even although it's near vacuum of space
你可以听到 尽管它是在接近真空的空间里
because of course the rocket exhaust is gas pressure and that's what's driving the microphones.
因为火箭的排气是气体压力 这就是驱动麦克风的原因
Now if they choose to share this and I'm not sure they will
现在 如果他们选择分享这个 我不确定他们会这样做
we would see this thing separate cleanly
我们会看到这个东西干净地分开
and then possibly the nozzle vector over and the thing light up and start spinning out of control.
然后可能是喷管的矢量 这东西亮了起来 开始失去控制地旋转
I think that would confirm everything we knew
我认为这将证实我们所知道的一切
but if they don't want to share it, it would be totally understandable.
但如果他们不想分享它 这将是完全可以理解的
They are in a commercial organization
他们是一个商业组织
and they can ill afford bad news, right.
他们不能承受坏消息 对吧
So Rocket Lab have been hugely successful in the small site launch market.
因此 火箭实验室在小型站点发射市场上取得了巨大的成功
They are pretty much the de facto launcher for small vehicles now
他们现在几乎是事实上的小型飞行器的发射者
but there's competitors now coming into this space
但现在有竞争对手进入这一领域
that have actually succeeded in demonstrating launch capabilities.
已经实际成功地展示了发射能力
The Virgin Orbit have done this
维珍轨道公司已经做到了这一点
and Astra have got so close that everyone expects the next one to actually fly to orbit.
和Astra已经如此接近 以至于每个人都期望下一个能真正飞向轨道
So there's competition at the low end of the market
因此 在低端市场上存在着竞争
but equally Rocket Lab are also losing a number of small sat launches to the Rideshare option that SpaceX offers.
但同样地 火箭实验室也失去了许多小型卫星发射的机会 被SpaceX提供的 "共享 "选项所取代
Now that's not for everyone, right.
现在 这并不适合所有人 对吧
If you're going on a Rideshare it may be cheaper
如果你要乘坐共享汽车 它可能更便宜
but you have to fly with a lot of other satellites
但你必须与许多其他卫星一起飞行
which may smell or out gas as they say in the technical terms.
这可能是他们在技术术语中所说的气味或气体不足
And then you may not get to pick the exact orbit you want.
然后你可能无法选择你想要的确切轨道
So that works for some people but it doesn't work for everyone.
所以这对一些人有用 但不是对所有人都有用
So it's easy to see that when Rocket Lab announced that
因此不难看出 当火箭实验室宣布
they were going to become publicly traded that the money they were going to get at from that
他们将成为上市公司 他们将从中获得的资金
was going to be invested in a bigger rocket the Neutron
将被投资于更大的火箭 "中子号
which should be able to carry 8 tons to orbit.
该火箭应能携带8吨重的物品进入轨道
Rocket Lab also have developed spacecraft buses
火箭实验室还开发了航天器总线
that can work in low earth orbit or even go to the moon or Venus.
可以在低地球轨道工作 甚至可以去月球或金星
The Photon spacecraft is something that SpaceX doesn't have anything like this for
光子航天器是SpaceX没有这样的东西的
and it's a very attractive feature if you're wanting to develop sensors to go to either of those destinations
如果你想开发前往这些目的地的传感器 这是一个非常有吸引力的功能
so Rocket Lab is a organization which is pretty well diversified in this front
所以火箭实验室是一个在这方面非常多元化的组织
and I think they're doing great
我认为他们做得很好
and it's unfortunate that they've had this anomaly.
很不幸的是 他们出现了这种异常情况
I mean we call it an anomaly.
我的意思是 我们称之为异常情况
When I hear the word anomaly
当我听到反常这个词时
I think of the delta II taking off and exploding
我就会想到德尔塔二号的起飞和爆炸
and then the voice of the public affairs officer saying we've had an anomaly.
然后公共事务官员的声音说 我们出现了异常情况
We have had an anomaly.
我们有一个异常点
No kidding, right.
别开玩笑了 对
But yeah I mean I'll take that by the way any day.
但是 是的 我的意思是 我随时都会接受这个说法
Over China's approach
比起中国的做法
which I've got to mention China successfully landed on Mars yesterday
我得提一下 中国昨天成功地在火星上登陆了
and depending how you count it
而且取决于你如何计算它
they are either the second, third or fourth nation to soft land something on Mars.
他们是第二个、第三个或第四个在火星上软着陆的国家
But yeah they had the Tianwen spacecraft in Mars orbit right now.
但是 是的 他们的 "天问 "航天器现在就在火星轨道上
The lander is called Zhurong.
着陆器被称为 "祝融"
And we actually knew that it was going to be landing
而我们实际上知道它将会登陆
because amateur satellite nerds had their receivers pointed at Mars
因为业余的卫星爱好者把他们的接收器对准火星
and they could actually see the carrier signal from this spacecraft
他们实际上可以看到来自这个航天器的载波信号
and they could see that it changed as it began the de-orbit burn
他们可以看到 当它开始脱离轨道燃烧时 信号发生了变化
so we knew that it was doing something and it was very likely landing.
所以我们知道它正在做一些事情 而且很有可能正在着陆
But there was nothing on Chinese media.
但是中国媒体上没有任何消息
No official announcement of anything until about half an hour after it had landed
直到它着陆后大约半小时 官方才宣布任何消息
and everybody else in the world knew that it was probably successful.
而世界上的其他人都知道它可能是成功的
Look so obviously congratulations to China for doing that.
显然 祝贺中国做到了这一点
I wish you were a little more self-confident and could perhaps handle some criticism.
我希望你能更自信一点 也许能处理一些批评
And I am actually really interested in what the ground penetrating radar on the rover delivers
实际上 我对漫游车上的地面穿透雷达提供的信息非常感兴趣
because I don't think we've seen anything like that on Mars before
因为我不认为我们以前在火星上看到过这样的东西
and obviously we're looking at a surface most of the time
很明显 我们大部分时间都是在看一个表面
but Mars has layers. It has depth and that could be some interesting stuff.
但是火星有层次 它有深度 这可能是一些有趣的东西
On Rocket Lab side, unfortunately you lost that.
在火箭实验室方面 不幸的是你失去了这个
I really hope the booster comes back and we get to see some more about how that works
我真的希望助推器能回来 我们能看到更多关于它是如何工作的
Rocket Lab their booster landing isn't like SpaceX.
火箭实验室他们的助推器着陆不像SpaceX那样
They ditched the booster or they detached the second stage at roughly the same time
他们抛弃了助推器 或者他们在大致相同的时间脱离了第二级
oh and by the way if you look at the telemetry
哦 顺便说一下 如果你看一下遥测数据
somebody pointed out that during the ascent
有人指出 在上升过程中
they throttle back the engines to maintain 3G during the launch last night
他们在昨晚的发射中节制了引擎以维持3G
whereas previous launches they've just kept the thing accelerating faster and faster
而以前的发射 他们只是让东西加速越来越快
and I don't know if that's something the customer requested
我不知道这是否是客户要求的东西
or if it's something that's being done to perhaps make the re-entry interface a little smoother
我不知道这是否是客户要求的 或者是为了使再入界面更顺畅而做的事情
but I mean the boosters that Rocket Lab recover
但我是说火箭实验室回收的助推器
they fall through the atmosphere unprotected.
他们在没有保护的情况下穿过大气层
They're not going to do an entry burn to slow them down to make the entry a little less rocky.
他们不会做一个进入燃烧来减缓它们的速度 以使进入时不那么颠簸
They use parachutes and then drogue parachutes and then large parachutes to land themselves in the ocean
他们使用降落伞 然后是降落伞 然后是大型降落伞 让自己降落在海洋中
and if they can demonstrate that it can handle re-entry and be flyable after that
如果他们能够证明它能够处理再入大气层 并且在那之后可以飞行
then the next step will be to capture those boosters as they fall with a helicopter
那么下一步将是在这些助推器下落时用直升机捕获它们
so that they don't touch the ocean and so they are much easier to clean up and reuse.
这样它们就不会接触到海洋 这样它们就更容易被清理和重新使用
And that would be great.
这将是伟大的
So yeah I hope that some success comes from this flight for you Rocket Lab.
所以 我希望你们火箭实验室在这次飞行中能取得一些成功
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是斯科特-曼利 飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]